Isn 't there a bridge around here ?
Pleased to meet you . Piotrek .
Ok , but my GPS ...
I 'll design you a new bridge when I get settled in .
Peter !
We can speak Polish .
You insisted on the old barn , keeping up with tradition .
Żaneta likes this place .
I 've sent down a digger . Ronaldo will help you .
Pour , Ronaldo ...
Listen ...
I think it 's all been too quick .
I know young people need to get to know each other .
Not shack up right away .
We love each other ...
- We don 't want to wait . - I 'm being totally frank with you .
I don 't know you .
A few Skype calls in English can hardly be called knowing someone .
But anyway ...
I hope Żaneta knows what she 's doing .
What can I do ? All I can do is wish you well .
Here 's the timetable .
Timetable ?
- Yeah , timetable . - Timetable .
Stop !
Don 't bother .
I 'll manage .
I 'll manage !
The keys to the house .
I 'll drive you back .
I 'll manage .
Wonderful !
Come here .
Come here !
- Cheers ! - Thanks .
It 's drizzling .
How cute ...
Drizzle , drizzling .
... one little cloud .
I know , I know ...
Piotr ?
Anybody here ?
Brother !
We 're just missing the swimming pool .
Bachelor boy !
Where are you ?
He 's hiding ...
Python !
Have you spoken to him ?
He 's vanished .
I don 't know , sister . Maybe he doesn 't love you anymore .
I 'd be scared of you .
Where 's everywhere ?
Wait . I 'll call you later .
Your brother-in-law is here !
You know what this means in Poland ?
Have you two met ?
Fuck ... My mother used to do it for me .
Go on . Pour some vodka .
See that ?
I , Żaneta ...
Take you , Piotr ...
as my husband .
As my husband .
To have and to hold ...
To love ,
honour ...
obey ,
for as long as we both shall live .
Not like that .
Zofia , Zygmunt ...
For mum and dad !
My dears !
I learned this song from my grandma !
Band please !
Who 's taking a wife ? He 's taking a wife ,
I won 't take a wife !
The boys will come to me ,
I won 't be asking them !
Who 's whining on life ? He 's whining on life ,
I won 't whine on life !
I 've got pounds in my pocket ,
and it 's all I need !
- Tip your head back . - What ?
Well , the groom 's just lost his cherry .
Let 's keep on dancing !
Music , maestro , please .
I love you .
Someone 's watching us .
He doesn 't mind .
Doesn 't mind ?
I can 't with grandpa watching .
Alright ! That 's enough !
Come on !
Hey boys ! No toys to play with ?
Enough !
I 'm sorry ...
Come on . Let 's get inside !
What ?
You seem different .
I 'm not Python any more , I 'm Piotr .
Did you forget ?
Kiss the groom !
Thank you , thank you ...
Now the professor would like to say a few words .
Please ... Bravo !
I 'd like to say ... On this special day ...
Louder !
Here ... Bravely !
Let me recall Stach , your grandfather , Żaneta .
He once said :
" Just wait 30 or 40 years .
We won 't have much of it ,
but our grandchildren will . "
He said it somewhere near here .
Right by this marquee .
I mean the marquee wasn 't there then ,
but when you leave the house it 's on the north-west side ...
Of course , Staszek wanted Żaneta to inherit this house .
It was his last will .
It 's a good bit of land .
And I confirm it .
I know a thing or two .
Listen to an old Jew .
I can still do my math .
Perhaps it 's good that it 's raining ,
because it reminds us of the tears of despair ,
of which there were many more than tears of joy .
We aren 't at school now !
I know , I know ...
Maybe it 's not the time .
But on the other hand ...
As Aristotle said :
" Whoever does not partake of society ...
is either a god ...
or a beast . "
There 's no man without society ...
and there 's no society without memory .
Beautiful words ...
Keep that memory in your hearts ...
Our thanks to the schoolteacher for those beautiful words !
And now ...
I 've got good news for you , my dears .
I won 't be singing this evening .
But seriously ...
I won 't propose a toast , because as you know
I don 't drink .
I won 't talk too long , because in my job all I ever say is :
" Don 't drink , don 't smoke " .
And no one listens to me anyway .
Instead , let the music speak for me .
Dear Żaneta and ...
- Piotr ! - I know ... Piotr .
And now a piece of music especially for you ,
which works better than aspirin , better even than Prozac .
I 'll stake all my medical diplomas .
Today I offer it without prescription .
- Play something Polish ! - Something funny !
Just a little glass ...
No ... One glass and then another .
I 've been there . Vodka and I are divorced
and I 've put it behind me .
It 's called the " irretrievable breakdown of the marriage . "
I 'm coming , I 'm coming !
Hey , Marzenka , Mariolka , we 're talking here !
What are you up to ? Looking for worms ?
- You think it 's funny ? - Yeah .
- Fuck off ! - Gents !
What 's up , gents ? First fight tonight ?
He 's got a problem .
Peter , what 's wrong ?
You ought to know , dad .
It was here .
But there 's nothing here .
There was a hole here a minute ago .
But what did it look like ?
Normally ...
Skeleton .
From a biology lab ?
- Yes , the same . - Yeah , from a biology lab !
Skeleton ... I recall now ...
It 's a dog .
Dad had three dogs .
He must have buried it in the garden . So it 's a dog .
I know what a dog looks like !
Alright , listen !
Let 's not all go abracadabra here .
Let 's say there 's something there ,
but we won 't start digging right now .
We 're drunk and we 'll drown in this mud .
We won 't see anything anyway .
We 'll do it when we 're sober .
For now , not a word .
Especially not to Żaneta .
Jasny !
Sit down !
Right . Talk .
Is this a wind-up ? Taking the piss ?
Course not ...
You always have some dumb ideas .
Back off , I don 't know anything .
What 's it all about then ?
- Maybe you know something ? - How the fuck should I know ?
You knew grandpa better than I did .
Just having a rest .
I feel trapped in a crowd like that .
I know how it might look .
The doctor sneaked out to have a drink on the sly .
But it 's not what it seems ... Who am I telling anyway ?
Sometimes it 's hard to exchange a word - never mind a thought - with anyone here .
Easy , easy ... Hyperventilation , nerves , stress . Typical .
Best get it out of your head ...
or better yet out of your stomach .
I have to tell you : The house is lovely , really lovely .
One thing !
Just have to eliminate the rain
and it will be perfect .
Did Żaneta 's grandfather build it ?
The house ?
No , it was here already .
I don 't get it .
Did you know her grandfather ?
Very decent man ...
As pure as the purss ...
As pure as the pursts ...
Fuck hell I can 't even ... You see ?
As pure as the purest driven snow .
Let 's be honest .
No one 's perfect . No one .
What happens when a white snowflake falls into a dirty puddle ?
I 'm an atheist .
I 'm interested in facts and analysis .
Ask the priest about abstraction .
- Thank you ... - Beautiful wedding .
Come here , your turn ...
Come here ! We 're waiting for you .
I 'm coming , I 'm coming .
Kiss the groom ! Kiss the groom !
You 'll get a kiss from me soon , mate !
My dears ...
Seems to be good son-in-law material ...
And he 's been recommended by my first-born .
He 's even promised to rebuild the bridge .
The one the Germans destroyed .
Ladies and gentlemen ...
Just like in any trade , it 's the same in life .
The young take their places , and the old ones let go .
No , no ...
We have to make room for the young .
There 's enough room , you can start on your own .
And your family next door will help you .
Change diapers and the potty .
In brief ...
Welcome home .
Wash your hands .
I 'll hang on to the digger though .
It 's harder to part with than my daughter .
Daddy ...
Your turn , Peter .
We 'll make good use of the digger .
You won 't minding if I ...
Won 't mind .
Won 't mind if I keep it a bit longer .
Just don 't take it to bed with you !
We don 't know each other well yet ...
The more I appreciate such a wonderful reception .
And ...
He 's lost the thread .
And I hope ...
We 'll live here for many years ...
Me ...
and Hana .
Who 's Hana ?
Żaneta , my honey !
You 've had enough , mate !
'Hana ' is what I call the digger .
Thank you father , thank you mother .
You brought me up beautifully .
It 's time for me to leave .
Bless me as I can 't come back now ...
The bride and groom !
Was Hana an old girlfriend ?
Planning to cheat on me already ?
No ... really ...
Where 's the ring ?
I think I know where you left it .
- Everything OK ? - Yes ... I feel a bit strange ...
Alcohol .
Polish wedding ... You 'd better dance it off .
Żaneta , I have to tell you something .
Now the groom will dance with the happy mother-in-law !
Change your partners !
No , no , no ...
No excuses ... It 's important .
Well , the bride groom 's spinning his mother-in-law around .
The first and last time . Poor old mother-in-laws .
What 's going on ?
I told them not to overdo it with the booze .
When they serve you tell them the best man will take it off your hands .
Change partners again !
The bride is waiting ...
I have a question ...
Is it possible ...
that the spirit of a dead person ...
can appear before us ?
How do you mean ?
Normally ...
There 's a spirit ...
and I can see it .
You mean the memory of a loved one ?
I know it sounds stupid , but ...
What 's this , Father ? Managed to sin already ?
I 'm sorry , I have to go ...
Please sit , Father , please ... I 'll come with a bottle in a minute .
But first a swift one with my son-in-law .
I can hardly talk to my son-in-law .
Either not around or talking to somebody else .
We have to get to know each other !
But it 's like drinking .
Only with your head not with an appetizer .
You should watch your mouth after you had a few .
Once it 's out it 's too late .
People start whispering and you don 't even know who started it .
It 's the butterfly effect .
There 's a theory : if a butterfly flaps its wings somewhere ,
it can cause a disaster .
Get out , get out !
- Do you know anything more ... - What about ?
About that skeleton .
You see how it sounds , depending on what words you use .
Then you 'll say you didn 't mean it .
But no one will hear you .
I know what I saw .
You saw it .
But I didn 't .
... and you bridesmaids take off your veils .
Just don 't ruin your hair ...
Make way !
And this morning by the church bells were chiming ...
Let 's roll him !
Just leave him .
Get ready .
Except you , kid .
You can 't either , dear uncle .
Jasny ! Jasny !
Doctor !
Piotr , it 's fine .
- We ought to take him . Just in case . - Don 't worry , boys . I 'll look after him .
You can 't take the groom away from his wedding .
It 's just epilepsy . Nothing serious .
Żaneta , has he had any attacks before ?
No , never ...
I mean ... Not since I 've known him .
You haven 't known each other long ...
Jasny , come here .
Listen , go and fetch more vodka from the car .
We 'll have to get everyone drunk . They can 't see the groom like this .
- How many bottles ? - All of them !
- Why all of ... - I said all of them !
Ronaldo !
Have them turn off that siren !
- Off you go , boys . - Are you sure you 're up to ... ?
Look at me . He 's in the care of a doctor .
When the stimulants kick in he 'll be as quiet as a lamb .
Have a good party ...
No use getting emotional .
Piotr ...
He 's not responding .
Give him time , Żaneta . He had a double dose .
It needs time .
He drank too much and maybe took something .
We shouldn 't take a blood test , it might cause problems , I reckon .
Piotr , is it OK ?
I 'll be back ...
Go on ! Don 't worry about a thing . Have fun !
Don 't worry , don 't worry ...
Relax , relax .
I won 't offer it to you ...
Take it ! And hurry up !
What did you give him ?
- I didn 't give him anything .. - Yeah , right !
Maybe he had something he took .
- I swear . - Fuck your promises .
A stupid joke of yours .
Even if I had something , he wouldn 't have taken it .
He doesn 't even drink much .
- Great . What 's up with him then ? - I don 't fucking know .
I 've never seen him like this .
Where the fuck are you going ? Fuck this !
Don 't you dare lie !
False alarm .
Everything 's fine . It 's under control .
Faster , faster !
As Piotr would say ...
Hurry up ! Move !
I 've put almost everything out . I left a few . For a rainy day .
Isn 't it fucking rainy enough ?
Well ? Start using your brain after thirty years .
What 's your problem ?
You found a fucked-up husband for you sister !
That 's the problem .
So it 's all my fault now .
Whose is it ?
Can 't you see he 's epileptic ?
How was I supposed to know ?
How were you supposed to know ?
How the fuck are you supposed to know anything ?
How much vodka are we left with ?
- Come dance ! - Hurry up !
- You got your duties as the best man ! - Wanna dance ? We 'll dance !
Where ?
Here ?
That 's what he said .
Really ?
I don 't know . Maybe he was making it up .
Didn 't you see how he was behaving ?
Why didn 't anybody tell me ?
But I thought you knew .
If it was me ...
I 'd have told you right away .
Keep playing !
Help him !
Ok , ok . I mean not OK . That was a heavy dose .
All right ... He 's not exactly well but we 'll figure it out .
Where 's that bloody son of mine ?
Piotr please tell me how can I help you ?
Żaneta ! Be careful !
Give him the fucking injection !
Haste makes waste .
Go on !
Now hold him steady .
What 's that ? Is he talking German ?
Talking in ... Foreign languages ...
Taiwan !
Go away !
Why 's the bloody priest here ?
- I thought ... - What ? What did you think with ?
- I 'm sorry ... - Piotrek found a skeleton in the ground .
You fucking idiot !
I didn 't tell her anything . Get off me , will you ?
I came to say goodbye . I 've got work to do tomorrow .
Listen ...
There 's no skeleton .
It 's the ravings of a sick mind .
Żaneta , except no one 's seen it . Apart from him .
Why don 't you ask him ?
- What skeleton ? - It might be a spirit .
He 's talking in a foreign language .
He 's talking German . Big deal . He talks English too and even Polish .
- That isn 't German . - Even better . He 's talking crap .
Could you say something , Father ?
Here we go !
Well , the doctor said it 's epilepsy .
I did - but I take it back . I 've never seen epilepsy like this , have you ?
It must be possible to explain it from a medical point of view .
Really ? How ? How do you explain it ?
I don 't know ... Food poisoning , neurosis , psychosis perhaps .
Esotericism might have something to say .
Split personality .
Schizophrenia .
Multiple personality .
Fascinating illness .
The mind , emotions and motivations . All of this becomes fragmented .
But cases like these don 't happen ... Do you understand ?
And if they don 't , then the groom 's in fact possessed .
Dears ... I 'll tell you ...
It is suspected to be a case of food poisoning .
Let me stress it has nothing to do with the food we 've been serving .
It was something he ate earlier . Probably while he was still ...
in London .
The last thing Żaneta and Piotr want is for you to be worried about it .
I fully understand your concern . My wife and I were afraid of what might happen ,
but the doctor has calmed our nerves .
As he has seen hundreds , maybe even thousands of such cases .
As we were leaving , the groom was racing back here
and actually wanted to dance .
But I ...
He needs to rest .
Saint Michael , the Archangel , defend us in battle ,
Be our defense against the wickedness and snares of the devil .
May God rebuke him , we humbly pray .
That 's Yiddish .
- Yiddish ? - Yes .
It 's too weak .
We need something more powerful . Maybe try something in Latin ?
Amen .
Are you out of your fucking mind ?
Let him go !
Saint Michael , the Archangel , defend us in battle ...
Be our defense against the wickedness ...
Professor , please ...
Yes ?
What do you mean " yes " ? Open the bloody door .
Let us in !
Are you crazy ?
Have you all gone fucking mad ?
He 's been shouting his head off .
Bring the band in , otherwise all the guests will come here if he keeps wailing .
Professor , please ...
Why drag him into this ?
Leave us alone . Now !
All right , all right ... As you wish .
Father , may I have a word ?
- I really have to go now . - Just a word !
Guys , stay a bit longer ! Where 's your boss ?
- Fuck ! - Not now !
Just a few more songs !
Everything 's packed away . What can we plug in there ?
There was a contract . Right ?
- With a timetable attached . Right ? - There was , but ...
But what ? I want music and fun .
Who pays the piper calls the tune .
Who are you ?
I 'm Hana .
I knew only one Hana here .
Everyone in the area courted her ...
I was also in love with her ...
We 'd bet about who would kiss her first ...
I can still feel her cheek ...
But she only loved one Polish boy ...
Then she vanished without a trace .
Who are you ?
I 'm Szymon Wentz .
I live in the house by the river .
You 're little Szymon ?
Under little Lilly 's cradle stands a pure white goat .
The little goat went to market ,
to buy you raisins and almonds .
... so you would fall asleep , my little boy .
What 's going on ? Nothing 's going on . Just a normal wedding .
The weather isn 't up to much , so few things went wrong .
We 're talking about the groom .
Why 's everyone on about the groom . The groom this , the groom that .
What is it - a stag night ?
Don 't you have better things to talk about ?
I saw the priest leave the cellar .
So what if he did ?
Anyone can leave . It 's a free country ...
Everyone can come and go as they please .
They say a Jewish demon has possessed the groom .
Who 's been spreading such nonsense ?
Next you 'll start to gossip .
You should be ashamed of yourself .
I said they should get to know each other .
Live together .
And why England ?
As if there weren 't any boys here .
It 's not your fault .
And if it 's true what they 're saying ?
Who ?
What sort of a wedding is it without a Jew ?
No , no ! I 'm not drinking .
That was all in Romanticism .
I 'll tell you something ...
In the old days mad men used to walk around ,
talk to ghosts , but no one was ever afraid of them .
Until later when they started to treat them as lepers .
In the old days it was all simple . Everyone was Polish .
Poland was as big as the whole world .
It was peaceful and happy .
And then the bad ghosts came in and divided all the Poles .
That is why our land was taken !
First Germany then Russia and then finally Israel !
Why have you taken over this man ?
He is my lover .
The one I was promised .
He is the husband of this girl here .
And what you 're doing ... Look at her .
I 'm not a rabbi ... I don 't have the power of a holy man ,
but I beg you :
leave this man 's body .
This is a different life .
Other people are being born and dying .
You 're lying ! My God .
I want to see my family .
That one no longer exists .
Neither do you .
Dad ...
Mom ...
Your family doesn 't exist .
Piotr ...
According to the timetable ... The wedding cake !
Get the fuck out !
Zygmunt ! It 's paid for .
Find out what 's up at the barn . And call an ambulance .
Your friend needs taking away .
That 's enough of that " friend " . I don 't know him very well .
Fine .
And we 're going downstairs .
I understand everything , but we can 't keep a sick man in the cellar all night .
He isn 't sick .
In Jewish tradition the soul of a dead person can cling to a living one ,
in order to carry out what death interrupted ...
It 's a dybbuk .
The clinging .
It 's the chance for it to purge itself ,
but also to purge the soul of the possessed one .
To purge is purgatory .
Only cutting that connection by exorcism ...
What the fuck are you talking about ?
So sorry , I apologize ...
This is very interesting .
But we live in the twenty-first century .
We live in a civilized country .
This is the case for health care !
Can 't you see that in a minute he 's going to croak ?
And we 'll all be fucking accused of refusing help to a sick person .
What will we tell them then ? That he saw a skeleton ?
What skeleton ? " I don 't know what skeleton .
I didn 't see it . But the patient did .
And then he had a seizure and did St. Vitus 's Dance ,
and talking crap in German ,
And then had epil ...
So we locked him in the cellar to talk about the epilepsy . "
Please let 's stop this nonsense .
Listen ...
Calm down ...
We 've agreed that according to the preliminary medical diagnosis ...
and with the consent of the priest ...
the marriage is annulled .
What did you say ?
Take it easy , Żaneta , easy ...
We ought to wait a while until the experts have had a look .
It may turn out he isn 't a lunatic .
I don 't say it won 't .
It may turn out he isn 't .
And then we 'll have another wedding .
A normal one , with sunshine and all .
And not here , I never really liked this land , honestly .
But above all we ought to find out something about his family .
Are you totally insane ?
I 'm not insane ! We ought to clear up who his parents were .
- Yes , of course ... - We ought to clear up !
- Yeah ! We ought to ! - We ought to clear up !
The doctor will get us a referral to a centre with the best specialists ...
Easy , easy ...
Don 't bother , let 's give her some time .
Everything will be fine .
They think I 'm dead .
But it 's not true .
It 's nice here , but I really have to go .
Of course . I 'll get someone to give you a lift home .
The ambulance is on its way .
I told them not to turn on the siren , so as not to make a racket .
Good .
And the barn 's almost ready . The rain 's easing off .
We 'll be able to move everyone back and quietly get him out of the cellar .
We have to drive the priest home .
- I 've been drinking . I can 't . - Ronaldo ?
So ?
- Don 't you have a driving license , Father ? - Well it just so happens .
The doctor can drive the priest home !
Doctor !
Did you drink anything today ?
Me ?
Are you sure you can drive ?
Of course .
I don 't see why not .
Welcome ...
Easy peasy .
I 'm as sober as a skunk , as they say .
By the way I don 't know why they say that :
" As sober as a skunk . "
It could be as sober as a horse , a dog , a dolphin ...
Any animal would do .
Let 's go , let 's go . Tomorrow belongs to us .
Be split , be accursed , broken and banned ...
Let 's go .
... you son of mud , son of clay ...
like Shamgaz , Merigaz and Istemaah ...
- Auntie Gizela , the party 's this way . - Get out of here .
- Żaneta ... - Doctor , let 's go already .
Żaneta , child , are you insane too ?
Leave me alone .
Dad , watch out , there 's mud .
Żaneta ... What are you doing ? There 's nothing there .
Are you going to start pulling skeletons out of the ground ?
Corpses ...
Exactly : corpses .
Perhaps there are more of them .
Maybe ... How do I know ? The whole country 's built on corpses .
You 're dad 's right ... Maybe it 's better to leave things be .
Żaneta , if there 's more of them , we might all go fucking nuts !
Żaneta , Żaneta ...
They deserve ...
decent burial .
Where ? How ? Why ? Who is there to bury ?
Who would come to the funeral ?
Only TV cameras looking for headlines .
He 's gone .
Who ?
He 's not in the cellar .
Fucking hell !
Dad ! He 's not here !
Let 's do the tango !
For better or worse
till death do us part !
Take everyone to the barn ! Search around the house !
I 'll search inside one more time .
Ladies and gentlemen !
The weather 's improved ,
so you can all go back to the barn .
To the barn !
- I don 't know ... He isn 't there . - Get the car !
- What 's going on ? - Hello , someone called us .
- Who ? Where ? - Where 's the patient ?
What patient ? Get out of here ! Fuck !
To the presbytery , please .
Jasny ! Come back ! He isn 't here !
Take the road behind the butcher 's .
Butcher ...
It used to be a synagogue .
Every day at dawn the tsaddik walked here ...
12 kilometres from his village .
He washed in the mikvah before entering the synagogue
so he could touch the Torah , and read the holy words .
All came to him for blessings :
Jews , Orthodox Christians and Catholics .
And Scheffer the butcher was here .
This was the Dalachs ' bakery .
" The best challah every Friday for regular customers " .
This way ...
Eliza , Sarka and Mela walked to school .
... Hana 's sisters .
The most beautiful girls I ever saw .
That was ... My whole world .
Almost nothing is left .
Only what 's in the memory .
And Janek also returned ...
To his beloved Lorcia ,
And rode to her gate ,
Come out Lorcia , darling ,
Her sister came out in green ,
" Your Lorcia is in the ground "
He searched all the graves
He rode to Lorcia 's grave ...
It 's all Descartes ' fault ...
Sod the entire Enlightenment .
It 's pointless .
Piotr !
As the Bible says :
When the soul leaves the body it wanders through dry places .
And it can 't find rest
and it won 't find it .
Come on Hana .
I 'm going to get us out of here .
Now I see the light .
Where are you going ?
Careful . It 's real wet out there .
Piotr !
Tell me something , you 're such a nice Jewish girl ...
and you chose Piotr ...
Why for instance , not me ?
Am I not good enough ?
I 'm a bachelor , no drinking habit , good social status ...
Fuck , I think I got lost , but calm down Hana , calm down .
Piotr !
Dearest guests .
Go back to your homes and sleep in peace .
We 'll wake up tomorrow ... When ...
When we open our eyes ...
Everything will be clear to us .
We just have to sleep it off .
We must forget ... What we didn 't see here .
Because ...
Because what we were eye-witnesses to ...
was only the effect of collective hallucination .
We think we took part in it ,
but we only think we did .
I 'm dreaming you .
And you 're dreaming me .
It 's quite simply just a collective dream .
A dream in a dream .
In fact there never was a wedding .
You weren 't here .
I wasn 't here ...
Neither isn 't there a groom .
And there never was .
One , two ...